Okay.
I wanted to discuss the persistence
aspect of algebraic datatypes and
actually any value in Haskell
and working with them.
And I will do this with this Tree example.
It's again the definition from the slides.
What has been added is this line here.
I added this and you will also
see this in exercise tasks.
Because I needed, if I want to print or show
the value of this type from the command line.
Yeah, this can always be added to an algebraic
datatype definition and then add some
printing facility.
Okay, as we will see in a moment.
Okay.
And other than that, here we have the
normal definition that you have seen before.
Okay, let me load this into the interpreter.
Okay, then, what can I do? Well, for
example, I can introduce some trees.
So, let's say I start with a
certain tree, a simple one.
And with the value 10.
And this is supposed to be an integer tree.
So that I then can use it for the insert example.
Okay, so 't1', this is my tree now.
Okay, and then what can I do, for example:
I can call the 'insert' function in order.
And that lets me bind the
result to some other tree.
And let me say, I want to insert 5 into 't1'.
Okay, then my 't2' now looks
like this, it is a 'Node'.
And the first argument is
'Node', which has the 5.
Which I've just inserted.
At the root, we still have the 10.
And the right subtree is still just a 'Leaf'.
And for example, I could do further things.
I could say: Well, into this, I actually want to
insert 12 and then my 't3' is something like this.
And I can go on and on.
Okay.
Now, the thing that I want to point out is
that 't1' and 't2' are completely unaffected by
these operations I have done in
order to get larger trees, right?
So, it's not like inserting 12 into 't2'
means that 't2' now contains the 12.
No.
't2' is still the tree it has always been.
It's just like if numbers and
equations between numbers, right?
If I do, if I say x is 5, and y is x + 3,
then of course, x doesn't become eight.
The y becomes eight.
The same happens here.
And it's different in many modeling or
relation approaches in imperative languages
for tree structures in particular,
where you could have pointer trees.
And then an insertion means
to change something in place.
Okay, for something like we see here could be
obtained in imperative languages
with cloning or defensive copying.
So, maybe you've heard of these
notions, this is not necessary here.
Because by default, and always, the language
concept is that things are immutable.
I also mentioned that this
need not worry you too much.
So, it's not like these three trees that
I now have are complete copies in memory.
That's not the case.
For example, 't2' and 't3' will share this part.
So, 't2' is this whole tree mathematically
and 't3' is this whole tree.
But if we were to look into the runtime
system to see how it is represented in memory,
then this part which is common between 't2' and
't3' will be stored only once in memory, right?
So, that is our pointer structure
and this is shared by a pointer.
But that's not something that is
visible from the language level.
Yeah, that's an implementation
detail for optimization purposes.
It has to do with the fact that in this
insertion function, sometimes I don't touch
some subtrees and then, of course, they can
be preserved and just reused via pointers.
And I only change the structure
along the path of inserted
values actually, or on the path to the
place where I have to insert the value.
But things are shared.
So, this is not represented twice.
But mathematically, 't2' and
't3' are separate trees.
So, whatever, if I do something.
So, let me say 't3', as I just
mentioned, shares this part with 't2'.
But of course, this does not mean that if I do
something to 't2', let's say I do a call 'insert'
and I want to insert 3 into 't2'.
What would this mean?
It would create this new tree, right?
So, we are now in this part, which
previously was this left successor of 't2'.
This now turns into this
because the 3 has been added.
But of course, this doesn't affect
't3', and it shouldn't affect 't3'.
Even though 't2' and 't3' share this part.
The fact that I have done something to
't2', or with 't2' doesn't change this.
So, 't3' is, of course, the tree of just the 5.
Yes, so what's happening here is sound
with respect to mathematical interpretation
of expressions, etc…; the
implementation, optimizations.
But they don't affect the
meaning of the programs.
So, what we see here is persistency.
So, doing something by creating a new tree as
a function call might give a new structure.
But the old thing is not overwritten,
or changed, or affected in some way.
Okay, and of course, the very same thing
applies to other data structures as well.
Also to lists.
Yes, so when we did things like insert something
into the list, we didn't insert into that list.
We created a new list, which
maybe shared some structure
with the original list but
contained another element.
Or if we even split the list, it didn't
mean that we really split the original list.
It meant that we created two new lists, each
of which contains half of the original list.
Or when we reverse the list,
that didn't mean that we really
changed the order of elements in that list.
It meant that we created a new list.
Which has reversed order.
How this is done efficiently, or how this may be
represented efficiently in memory
is not our concern as programmers.
I mean, when you become a more mature
and advanced programmer, you may
want to think about some details like this.
But at the moment, we think about
expressiveness and about what programs mean.
And then we don't have to concern
ourselves with these details.
So, we think about the values, the
expressions, and the values that they have.
And then the important thing is that
things are immutable or, as it's called
in algorithmics, they are persistent.
As you see here, if you wanted to, et cetera.
And 't2' and 't3' are sharing a structure,
but if I insert something into 't2', which
basically just means that I create
a new tree, which was output here,
and this changes neither 't2' itself nor
't3', which shared some structure with 't2'.
Okay, unlike in object-oriented languages often.